<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A proclamation anent conventicles. Edinburgh, the third day of February, one thousand six hundred and seventy.</title>
            <author>Scotland. Privy Council.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1670</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 3 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B05492</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S1628B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R183361</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">52529251</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 52529251</idno>
            <idno type="VID">178988</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B05492)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 178988)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2775:59)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A proclamation anent conventicles. Edinburgh, the third day of February, one thousand six hundred and seventy.</title>
                  <author>Scotland. Privy Council.</author>
                  <author>Scotland. Sovereign (1649-1685 : Charles II)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Evan Tyler, Printer to the Kings most excellent Majesty,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1670.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Royal arms at head of text; initial letter.</note>
                  <note>Intentional blank spaces in text.</note>
                  <note>Signed at end: Al. Gibson, Cl. Sti. Concilii.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the National Library of Scotland.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Conventicle Act, 1670.</term>
               <term>Church and state --  Scotland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Assembly, Right of --  Scotland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Broadsides --  Scotland --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="royal_proclamation">
            <pb facs="tcp:178988:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 15 -->
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <head>C R</head>
                  <q>DIEV ET MON DROIT</q>
                  <q>HONI SOIT QUI MAL Y PENSE</q>
                  <figDesc>royal blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <head>A PROCLAMATION, Anent CONVENTICLES.</head>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> 
                  <date>the third day of <hi>February,</hi> one thouſand ſix hundred and ſeventy.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>HARLES,</hi> by the Grace of GOD, King of <hi>Great Britain, France</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> Defender of the Faith;</signed>
               <salute>To <gap reason="blank" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈1 span left blank〉</desc>
                  </gap> Macers or Meſſengers at Armes, conjunctly and ſeverally ſpecially con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute, Greeting.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Foraſmuch as We have taken to conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, the diſorderly carriage of ſeveral Heretors, outed Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, Tennents and others of the Commons within this Kingdom, by their keeping of Conventicles, and baptizing of their Children by perſons not authorized or allowed; which not only foment and nouriſh Separation and Schiſm, but tend to Sedition, and the diſturbance of the publick Peace. Do therefore, with advice of the Lords of Our Privy Council, require all Sheriffs, Stewarts, Bailiffs of Regalities and their Deputes, Magiſtrates of Burghs in their reſpective bounds, and the Commiſsioners of the <hi>Militia,</hi> To inform them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves where ſuch Conventicles have been keeped ſince the nineteenth day of <hi>October</hi> laſt, or ſhall happen to be keeped hereafter, and to call before them the Miniſters who have preached or ſhall preach at them, the Heretors or ſubſtantial Tennents who have been or ſhall be preſent thereat, or have had their Children baptized ſince the ſaid nine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth day of <hi>October,</hi> or ſhall procure them to be baptized by any not allowed or autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rized to do the ſame; and according as they ſhall find any of them guilty, that they take caution of them for their appearance before Our Privy Council, when ever they ſhall be called: And in caſe any of them, being called before the ſaids Sheriffs, Stewarts, Bailiffs or Magiſtrates foreſaids, or before the ſaids Commiſsioners of the <hi>Militia,</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear not, or compearing ſhall refuſe to give caution, That they, with advice and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence of the Captain, Lieutenant or Cornet of any of the <hi>Militia</hi> Troops of the Shire, ſeize upon their perſons, and ſend them to the Lords of Our Council by a Party of the <hi>Milit<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a;</hi> Which Party ſhall be payed at eighteen ſhillings <hi>Scots</hi> a day for each Horſeman, and three ſhillings <hi>Sterling</hi> for the Officer who ſhall command, from the time of their ſetting forth to their return: And that they ſend alongſt with them any proofs or evidences they have received of their guiltineſs: And Ordains the ſaids Sheriffs, Stewarts, Bailiffs, Magiſtrates and Commiſsioners of the <hi>Militia,</hi> from time to time, to give an account of their diligence to Our Council: And that theſe preſents be printed, and publiſhed at the Mercat-croſs of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> and other places needful, that none pretend ignorance.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Al. Gibſon,</hi> Cl. S<hi rend="sup">ti</hi> Concilii.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>EDINB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RGH,</hi> Printed by <hi>Evan Tyler,</hi> Printer to the King's moſt Excellent Majeſty, 1670.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
